<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-20T17:40:48+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">R O M V L V S</title><subtitle>A city building game that gives you incredible detail on huge maps.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">ROMVLVS v0.1 alpha release</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/08/20/ROMVLVS-v0.1-alpha-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ROMVLVS v0.1 alpha release" /><published>2019-08-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/08/20/ROMVLVS-v0.1-alpha-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/08/20/ROMVLVS-v0.1-alpha-release.html">&lt;p&gt;If you like free downloads and use macOS, check out the latest ROMVLVS 
release in the &lt;a href=&quot;/downloads.html&quot;&gt;downloads&lt;/a&gt; section!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I promise there will be releases for Windows and Linux as well 
in the future :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">If you like free downloads and use macOS, check out the latest ROMVLVS release in the downloads section!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A new alpha release coming soon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/17/a-new-start.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A  new alpha release coming soon" /><published>2019-07-17T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/07/17/a-new-start</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/17/a-new-start.html">&lt;p&gt;As usual, it’s been a while since I worked on ROMVLVS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My handle is now &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;keepitwiel&lt;/code&gt; as opposed to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CaptainHennessey&lt;/code&gt;. I am now 
the proud founder of Keepitwiel Studios!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve moved the blog/website to Github Pages, but the older blog 
still lives at &lt;a href=&quot;https://romvlvsgame.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt;. I might
move that content here at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m putting the finishing touches on a new alpha release (v0.1) that can be
freely downloaded.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As usual, it’s been a while since I worked on ROMVLVS.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A 400x400 map in ROMVLVS</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/01/a_400x400_map.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A 400x400 map in ROMVLVS" /><published>2017-08-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-08-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/08/01/a_400x400_map</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/01/a_400x400_map.html">&lt;blockquote class=&quot;imgur-embed-pub&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot; data-id=&quot;a/6pGIH&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;//imgur.com/a/6pGIH&quot;&gt;A 400x400 map in ROMVLVS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah the GIF takes a while to load, but at least you get a sense of 
what the engine is capabe of at the moment. I use Numpy to handle 
all the low level storing of data which is pretty fast - even at 
this size, I haven’t had any scaling issues so far.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A 400x400 map in ROMVLVS</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ROMVLVS engine philosophy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/30/ROMVLVS_engine_philosophy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ROMVLVS engine philosophy" /><published>2017-07-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/30/ROMVLVS_engine_philosophy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/30/ROMVLVS_engine_philosophy.html">&lt;p&gt;In short, I aim for ROMVLVS to be some sort of SimCity++, taking you from 
prehistoric to modern times while also invoking some Civ-like concepts 
such as research and warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ROMVLVS, like the original SimCity, leans heavily on the idea of cellular 
automata. Basically, simple rules governing the contents of tiles lead to 
very complex behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original concept popularized by Conway is very binary (either life 
exists on a tile or not); SimCity made use of difference equations in 
order to increase or decrease the quantity of e.g. population on a tile. 
This is the same in ROMVLVS. A simplified set of equations might look like 
this (&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;y&lt;/code&gt; are quantities to be increased/decreased, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;t&lt;/code&gt; is time, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;t+1&lt;/code&gt;
 is the time at the next turn):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;x(t+1) = x(t) + C1 * x(t) + C2 * y(t)
y(t+1) = y(t) + C3 * x(t) + C4 * y(t)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In SimCity you were free to build wherever you wanted, as long as you had 
enough money to do so. The existing infrastructure generates taxes, which 
fills the city coffers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ROMVLVS, there is no money. Or, at least, not centralized. If you don’t 
have resources available in a specific tile to build something, you can’t 
build it, even though it’s available on other tiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do resources spread around? This is where dispersion comes in place. 
Think of an inflatable pool in your back yard. When you pierce it, it will 
empty out in rapid pace, flooding its surroundings. The more time goes by, 
the more dispersed the water is, eventually flooding your entire garden 
with a thin layer of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ROMVLVS, dispersion works as follows: if you have a farm producing 1 
unit of food per turn, a small percentage of that (say 10%) gets dispersed 
to the four surrounding tiles. Your farm will be left with 0.9 units while 
its neighbors get 0.025 units each. Those neighboring tiles will disperse 
10% of 0.025 to their neighbors in the next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to keep infinitisemally small amounts of resources spreading 
around the map, there’s a dispersion threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of a game, you start with a Settlement and 5 people (all 
living in the Settlement). The Settlement produces Culture (quite an 
abstract resource) which starts spreading outward over time. The difference 
equation governing the growth of people is such that Culture is a positive 
factor - i.e.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Humans = Humans + CULTURE_FACTOR * Culture&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, resources like Food have also a similar positive influence whereas 
proximity to enemies, extreme temperatures etc. will negatively impact 
human growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This basically describes the ROMVLVS engine. The trick is to balance out 
all the different resources: adjusting growth and dispersement parameters, 
adding buildings that modify growth even further, and adding resources that 
counterbalance other resources. So far, only Culture, Humans, Food and Wood 
are “active” resources that can be altered; I’ve thought about adding things 
like Disease, Fear, Stone, Bronze, Meat, Fruit, etc. etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope you enjoyed this behind-the-scenes look!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In short, I aim for ROMVLVS to be some sort of SimCity++, taking you from prehistoric to modern times while also invoking some Civ-like concepts such as research and warfare.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ROMVLVS - building only farms</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/29/building_only_farms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ROMVLVS - building only farms" /><published>2017-07-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/29/building_only_farms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/29/building_only_farms.html">&lt;blockquote class=&quot;imgur-embed-pub&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot; data-id=&quot;a/LudrQ&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;//imgur.com/a/LudrQ&quot;&gt;ROMVLVS - building only farms&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New in ROMVLVS: farms. The food they produce increases the 
population significantly. Here’s a GIF to show you how it works!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">ROMVLVS - building only farms</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ROMVLVS screenshots</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/27/ROMVLVS_screenshots.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ROMVLVS screenshots" /><published>2017-07-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/27/ROMVLVS_screenshots</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/27/ROMVLVS_screenshots.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017-07-27_screenshot_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anno Romuli 0. Your world is empty, save for the asterisk shaped 
tile which is your Settlement. It will start emanating Culture 
which in turn allows the population surrounding your settlement 
to grow over time. The white-on-pink Omega symbol indicates the 
cursor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017-07-27_screenshot_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pressed Enter a few times to let the city populate itself. The 
faces in the top middle indicate the population under the cursor 
(here highlighted by the white letter ‘F’ - which will build a 
Farm on that tile when pressed). Note we built quite a few farms 
around the settlement. The pink house-shaped symbol indicates 
people are living there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017-07-27_screenshot_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A civilization is born! We also built a Logger (Omega symbol) to 
produce wood, and Walls (stripy white blocks) to protect our city. 
There’s a lot of wood currently under the cursor, indicated by the 
green Ws in the top middle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ROMVLVS v0.0.4 release</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/06/ROMVLVS-v0.0.4-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ROMVLVS v0.0.4 release" /><published>2017-07-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/06/ROMVLVS-v0.0.4-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/06/ROMVLVS-v0.0.4-release.html">&lt;p&gt;After a hiatus of almost 2 years, I picked up the slack and made 
some long-needed updates and fixes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game can be downloaded here: https://drive.google.com/open?id=1Ij5XNUwo0A5GtjUbetVDTnXojj_90VWN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notable-changes&quot;&gt;Notable changes:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Game doesn’t break when you hit an unrecognized key&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changed appearance (10x10 pixel tiles were very tiny)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changed game engine - added “culture” layer which is generated 
by humans and allows for spreading of your civilization, up to a 
point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-install&quot;&gt;How to install:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please see previous post on how to run it (basically, extract 
contents of .zip archive, then double click the “run” file - 
execute directly or from terminal is fine)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s still for Linux only (specifically, it was developed and 
tested in Lubuntu 16.04 at 2880x1800 pixels)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quick-walkthrough&quot;&gt;Quick walkthrough:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://imgur.com/a/BG1bF&quot;&gt;http://imgur.com/a/BG1bF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might have to move your cursor around to find the piece of 
land that’s visible to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope you like it - and please send me feedback if you have any!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers - Captain Henessey&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">After a hiatus of almost 2 years, I picked up the slack and made some long-needed updates and fixes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ROMVLVS v0.0.3 release</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2015/12/06/ROMVLVS-v0.0.3-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ROMVLVS v0.0.3 release" /><published>2015-12-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-12-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2015/12/06/ROMVLVS-v0.0.3-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2015/12/06/ROMVLVS-v0.0.3-release.html">&lt;p&gt;Hey!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks very much for checking out this first playable release of ROMVLVS, 
a simulator game!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s currently in alpha stage (v0.0.3) so lots of bugs have to be ironed 
out and features added. If you see a bug or think of a feature, don’t 
hesitate to contact me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-run-in-linux&quot;&gt;To run in Linux:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download the following file: https://drive.google.com/file/d/0BzJPRrTQDddjOVJxbWI4ek9uR0k/view?usp=sharing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unzip downloaded file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double click ‘run’ in the directory of the unzipped files&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the popup that appears, click ‘Execute’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To exit the game, This was tested successfully in Lubuntu, it might work 
for other Linux distros as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As of now, no other operating systems are supported.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ROMVLVS is a civilization simulation game, merging the low level 
modularity of SimCity with the high level strategy of games like 
Civilization. There are no centralized elements: you don’t found a city, 
a city emerges from large populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each tile roughly represents an area of 10x10m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no explicit game objectives. Population grows automatically at 
the end of every turn but will level off quite soon unless you build 
buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-mechanics&quot;&gt;Game mechanics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Population &lt;em&gt;on a tile&lt;/em&gt; grows when it’s nearby water. It levels off if there 
are too many people on a tile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Population &lt;em&gt;disperses to neighboring&lt;/em&gt; tiles when there are more than 5 
people on a tile. The game currently works with decimal numbers, make of 
that what you will. Materials like food and wood distribute in the same 
manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without buildings, you’re essentially growing a hunter-gatherer society. 
They don’t produce excess food or materials and are in touch with nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buildings&quot;&gt;Buildings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buildings you can build to advance your civilization are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Farm - creates surplus food. Costs population&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Logger - creates surplus wood. Costs population&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Settlement - increases population. Costs wood&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wall - does nothing for now, in the future will protect against enemies. Costs wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-improvemens&quot;&gt;Future improvemens&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make the following improvements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t disperse materials to an unpopulated tile&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add enemies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a toggleable “heatmap” so you can clearly see the distribution of materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add roads&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please let me know if you think of any cool features that belong on this list!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Hey!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quick recap</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/12/25/quick_recap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quick recap" /><published>2014-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2014/12/25/quick_recap</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2014/12/25/quick_recap.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2014-12-25_romvlvs_development_screenshot_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;The player map with stats on the side.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Quick recap: I’m trying to build a Civilization/SimCity crossover, 
combining the bottom-up fun of SimCity with Civ’s top-down joy of 
conquering the world.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long overdue update. I renamed the game from Civpy, which was 
really just a working title, to ROMVLVS (notice the ancient Latin 
spelling of the letter ‘U’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also gave up on pixel art (Python/Pyglet) and rebuilt the game 
around a cool true-color ASCII based engine called libtcod. 
Fortunately, it’s available for Python so I could sorta easily weasel 
the library into the existing code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason for this is speed, both in true game speed as well as 
development speed. I just couldn’t get Pyglet to operate fast enough 
with my limited knowledge of programming, and libtcod gets around 
that by being precompiled. Also putting pixels in PNGs is very 
laborous and tiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter ASCII. For some reason being limited to 256 characters is very 
liberating. Two games currently are major sources of inspiration: 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ultimaratioregum.co.uk&quot;&gt;Ultima Ratio Regum&lt;/a&gt; 
and Cogmind (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gridsagegames.com/blog/2014/03/ascii-art/&quot;&gt;this excellent post&lt;/a&gt; 
on ASCII-based games by Cogmind’s developer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both games are roguelikes. I don’t like roguelikes that much, 
especially if they involve fantasy creatures like orcs, dwarves, 
goblins etcetera. What I like about roguelikes though is that they 
have a very clear focus on graphical aesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you see in this photo is the player map with some tile stats on 
the side, such as altitude and temperature. These stats are important 
as they will give you a clue how suitable the tile is for different 
types of buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this game there are 5 people living under the ’@’ character. I 
haven’t built anything yet but at this point there are 2 options: a 
settlement or a farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A settlement provides shelter which helps with population growth in the 
area. A farm just increases population growth on its own tile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both cost wood to build, and the caveat is that you can only use wood 
from your direct surroundings. So naturally I would need a logging 
station nearby as an additional building. That one sorta works (I 
already tried it), but I’m not satisfied with its dynamics. Basically 
you would need to build swathes of loggers in concentric circles around 
wherever your city center is, which is not very fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m working on a Mac, and the problem is that libtcod is only available 
for Windows and Linux. So for now I’m developing/running this game on a 
VM Lubuntu instance. I’ll try to make the game available for download 
as soon as I figure out how to bundle it :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I probably need to overhaul the GUI because it’s very hard to know 
what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading and stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hi</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/07/06/hi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hi" /><published>2014-07-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-07-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2014/07/06/hi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2014/07/06/hi.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the future&lt;/strong&gt;: this post was originally found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://romvlvsgame.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/civpy_screenshot_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial state of a Civpy game.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/civpy_screenshot_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;The same world with a small village.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi, I’m Captain Hennessey, creator of Civpy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Civpy is a civilization game, written in Python. It’s going to have a 
flashier name but Civpy will do for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also keeping it open source for now, to see where it goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above you see two images. The first is a randomly generated world with 
a tiny house. This is the initial state of each Civpy game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next image shows the same world, only with the house evolved into a 
small village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I want to make: a civ game on an expansive map that’s very 
detailed at the same time. Cities aren’t just one tile (as was the case 
in the old Civilization franchise) but are a collection of buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each tile represents about the same size as a SimCity tile, which is 
around 1 acre. (So yes, if I want a map to represent an entire planet, 
we’ll need around 1m x 1m tiles—let’s park that thought for now)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map is generated by a randomized algorithm. First it generates an 
altitude map, based on which other maps are generated (temperature, 
biomass, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is that humans naturally start spreading around, but that the 
rate of spreading is limited by the surroundings: if there’s not enough 
biomass or arable land around, the population capacity per tile is capped. 
Also, “wilderness” is a factor: if you live on the edge of town, you’re 
more exposed to bad elements like wolves, barbarians etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, now some background about me and my motivation to make this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we all know, game design involves a lot of hard choices, cursing and 
drinking. To make things worse, I’m not a good programmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choice #1: Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python is a little slow but there’s a lot of useful modules available such 
as Cocos2d. So basically all of the graphics and interface handling are 
done by Cocos2d. Later I will try to employ Cython to speed up the game, 
as well as directly use OpenGL to specifically speed up the graphics (it’s 
painfully slow on big maps and a reason why I can’t go beyond 64x64 
currently).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choice #2: Graphics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tiles are 16x16 pixels. Yes that resolution hasn’t been fashionable 
since the late ‘80s but it speeds up art development significantly. The 
trick is to make each pixel count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choice #3: No visible actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the game state is stored in a bunch of two-dimensional arrays. You 
won’t see tiny figures running around (at least not for now). I figured it 
was going to take a lot of effort modeling individual characters (peasants, 
lumberjacks, smiths whatever) as they go about their business. Instead I 
chose for a SimCity-like approach, where (for example) population in one 
tile depends on the amount of food in the surrounding tiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choice #4: No AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe later :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, I hope to update as much as possible!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Note from the future: this post was originally found on Tumblr.</summary></entry></feed>